<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>interactive | Liz Roten</title>
    <link>https://lizroten.com/tag/interactive/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://lizroten.com/tag/interactive/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>interactive</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Liz Roten 2024</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://lizroten.com/media/icon_hu9684a0c7728a1791553eb63a20e70951_11434_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>interactive</title>
      <link>https://lizroten.com/tag/interactive/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transportation System Performance Evaluation (TSPE)</title>
      <link>https://lizroten.com/project/tspe/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lizroten.com/project/tspe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Transportation System Performance Evaluation is a comprehensive review of the Twin Cities transportation system. It is required by state law to be completed before every Transportation Policy Plan (TPP) update.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TSPE contains data from a variety of sources, including demographic context from the US Census, comparisons to peer regions from national data sources, data from local agencies and researchers, and travel data from the Council’s Travel Behavior Inventory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;features&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All figures and tables are indexed and hyperlinked in Appendix&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All plotly figures are available for high-resolution PDF download&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This report is a comprehensive review of the Twin Cities transportation system as prepared by Metropolitan Council in 2023. The Minnesota State Legislature adopted statutes in 1996 requiring the Metropolitan Council to produce this report (previously called the Transportation System Audit). This report was prepared to inform the 2024 update to the region’s long-range transportation plan, the 2050 Transportation Policy Plan (2050 TPP).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;











&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-tspe&#34; href=&#34;https://lizroten.com/media/albums/tspe/layout.png&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lizroten.com/media/albums/tspe/layout_hu04595687d392f1619827101d3a3a8d0b_391853_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;layout.png&#34; width=&#34;338&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-tspe&#34; href=&#34;https://lizroten.com/media/albums/tspe/single-page.png&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lizroten.com/media/albums/tspe/single-page_hu04595687d392f1619827101d3a3a8d0b_453460_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;single-page.png&#34; width=&#34;338&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19 Surveillance at the Metro Plant</title>
      <link>https://lizroten.com/project/covid-poops/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lizroten.com/project/covid-poops/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In early 2022, my team was approached by scientists in the Council&amp;rsquo;s Environmental Services (ES) division for assistance. Throughout the pandemic, ES and the University of Minnesota Genomics center tracked viral genetic material in metro wastewater. The data was relatively uniform, but existing reports were internal facing and written for a highly technical audience. The ES team wanted to make the data more readily available, easily understandable, and easy to explore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a matter of days, my team assembled a prototype R Shiny app and began collaborating on GitHub. We made the repository public, and I used my expertise in R Shiny to develop an interactive data visualization tool. I completed onboarding git training with a new colleague and set up GitHub best practices and workflows, like using feature based branches, completing pull requests with code reviews, and using sustainable data storage. I managed community submitted GitHub Issues and facilitated code contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, I created a GitHub Actions workflow that automatically checks for package dependencies and securely deploys the app to our &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rstudio.com/products/shinyapps/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;shinyapps.io&lt;/a&gt; account. I configured the app on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rstudio.com/products/shinyapps/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;shinyapps.io&lt;/a&gt; to handle flash traffic and scale easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;awards&#34;&gt;Awards&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In March 2022, my teammates and I were awarded the &amp;ldquo;Keystone Award&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A cross-functional team came together to effectively share our monitoring data on the Met Council&amp;rsquo;s COVID-19 wastewater surveillance webpage and with the media. They conducted the science; compiled, visualized, and shared the data; and communicated about the work externally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Keystone Award recognizes employees who demonstrate exceptional work performance. This award recognizes employees for being good ambassadors for the agency and for delivering unique, exceptional and inspired projects that reflect well on the agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;media-coverage-and-community-response&#34;&gt;Media coverage and community response&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of June 2022, the COVID wastewater monitoring project page on &lt;a href=&#34;https://metrocouncil.org/Wastewater-Water/Services/Wastewater-Treatment/COVID19-Research.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;metrocouncil.org&lt;/a&gt; is the highest viewed page in the organization&amp;rsquo;s history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;How wastewater works to detect COVID, other viruses in Minnesota&amp;rdquo; by Jeremy Olson, Star Tribune &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.startribune.com/how-wastewater-works-to-detect-covid-other-viruses-in-minnesota/600190785/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Poop surfaces as crucial tool to track Twin Cities COVID&amp;rdquo; by David H. Montgomery, Minnesota Public Radio News &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mprnews.org/story/2022/01/14/covid-wastewater-twincities&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;In Sewage, Clues to Omicron’s Surge&amp;rdquo; by Emily Anthas and Sabrina Ambler, The New York Times &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2022/01/19/health/covid-omicron-wastewater-sewage.html?unlocked_article_code=AAAAAAAAAAAAAAAACEIPuonUktbfqYhkSVUaCibVUNEjsh3Bjv_RwbB5gXr_JzKST3Ndxv8JDpeJ50rXILFueNI80nKbWNpFevcJdcBF89V-bQZrWhX65dyNgogEKCE47om5UDhpj5zBGLwyrGevM2CzdKIvmLGz-kzeYDbsDfTe13UlIh134scwLSHc0nINxq_HFu5zy4M-ia9nXsYmMG9GMCqavPDoCAF8OMGGb3zf7Qo2XOJeWFLDjILWquJAIEgJVwWwHD4o6n086dhcJNoXIK_-ShYkc8H6irkSYXd6ihjRGr2Mj4nU_LE1Fh4taw&amp;amp;smid=url-share&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I think this is just fascinating, but after diving in, I&amp;#39;m most interested in the fact that the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/MetCouncilNews?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@MetCouncilNews&lt;/a&gt; named their GitHub repository &amp;quot;covid poops&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/17KoXgbfir&#34;&gt;https://t.co/17KoXgbfir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Nick (@NKroegs) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/NKroegs/status/1483813481514258433?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;January 19, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;recent-data&#34;&gt;Recent data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Metropolitan-Council/covid-poops&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;public repo&lt;/a&gt; for the most recent data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Metropolitan-Council/covid-poops/main/fig/cases_vs_load_large.png&#34; alt=&#34;Filled area and line plot comparing the total viral load in metro wastewater and COVID-19 cases&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Metropolitan-Council/covid-poops/main/fig/copies_by_variant_large.png&#34; alt=&#34;Filled area plot showing viral load in wastewater by variant type&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Metropolitan-Council/covid-poops/main/fig/variant_frequency_large.png&#34; alt=&#34;Line plot showing variant frequency in wastewater by variant type &#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regional Truck Corridor Study</title>
      <link>https://lizroten.com/project/truck-corridor-study/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lizroten.com/project/truck-corridor-study/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The study update process began in 2021 with a few goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Migrate existing calculations and documentation scattered in Excel workbooks, ArcGIS documents, and PDFs to reproducible R code and RMarkdown documents, complete with version control and testing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Re-score existing corridors using most recent available data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluate new truck corridors and freight facilities as submitted by agency partners.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the process, I carefully balanced preserving the original methodology and accounting for each data source&amp;rsquo;s quirks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some data used in the original study were unavailable. Working with our transportation planners, I developed a method for estimating truck volume and truck percentage of total traffic using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.streetlightdata.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;StreetLight Data&lt;/a&gt;. I then carefully integrated the data sources and patched missing data to complete the project. Finally, I completed an comprehensive project wrap-up, tracking down emails, chat messages, and meeting notes to compile a definitive &amp;ldquo;how&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;why&amp;rdquo; for each data source and analysis method. I used &lt;a href=&#34;https://groundhogr.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{groundhog}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to preserve package versions and implemented a clever script naming convention to organize files. Documentation is a love letter to your future self - and I went all out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;interactive&#34;&gt;Interactive&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to build the visualization using Tableau because I wanted to take advantage of Tableau&amp;rsquo;s dynamic tooltips, in which you can insert a mini plot. The interaction between elements, such as a map and a table, is more streamlined. Tableau can also turn out a snazzy visualization relatively quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;screenshots&#34;&gt;Screenshots&lt;/h3&gt;











&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-truck-corridor-study&#34; href=&#34;https://lizroten.com/media/albums/truck-corridor-study/corridor_179.PNG&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lizroten.com/media/albums/truck-corridor-study/corridor_179_huf9c119ed56b43bc7835bd6044b532550_269136_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;corridor_179.PNG&#34; width=&#34;235&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-truck-corridor-study&#34; href=&#34;https://lizroten.com/media/albums/truck-corridor-study/corridor_232.PNG&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lizroten.com/media/albums/truck-corridor-study/corridor_232_hu7da22254c19e816a38c61d784322e9cf_264088_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;corridor_232.PNG&#34; width=&#34;238&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-truck-corridor-study&#34; href=&#34;https://lizroten.com/media/albums/truck-corridor-study/freight_facilities.PNG&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lizroten.com/media/albums/truck-corridor-study/freight_facilities_hudeec7288ccc83c37c9d14e22eec82795_383450_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;freight_facilities.PNG&#34; width=&#34;239&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regional truck freight corridors were initially developed through the 2017 Regional Truck Highway Corridors Study. A technical advisory work group of public agency staff most directly engaged in highway planning guided this data-driven study that analyzed the region’s principal and minor arterials. Ultimately the study applied four data factors to establish corridor score rankings and to group the corridors into tiers 1, 2, and 3, in order of priority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2018 the Met Council adopted the study’s final regional truck corridors into the Transportation Policy Plan and first applied the tiered corridors as project selection criteria in the Regional Solicitation process for distributing federal transportation funds. The corridors have also been used as qualifying criteria in recent funding cycles of MnDOT’s Minnesota Highway Freight Program.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regional Parks and the American Community Survey</title>
      <link>https://lizroten.com/project/regional-parks-acs/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lizroten.com/project/regional-parks-acs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In May 2019, I completed an R Shiny app visualizing regional parks and trails in context with American Community Survey (ACS) demographic data. The project&amp;rsquo;s first iteration was built as a mini-app to be used in workshop sessions with regional parks implementing agencies. Later, I re-structured the backend to follow the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ThinkR-open/golem&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{golem}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; framework&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regional Parks and the American Community Survey is a mini-app designed for use by Regional Parks implementing agencies to assist in their progressing toward a more equitable use of regional parks. The app complements the Regional Parks Equity Toolkit, a set of questions and a process to clarify how regional park projects are advancing equity. The app facilitates direct examination of regional parks and trails system and the demographic characteristics of the census tracts surrounding them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-developments&#34;&gt;New developments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I transitioned to my split between Community Development (CD) and Metropolitan Transportation Services (MTS) divisions, another team member took the project on. I supported that person in building skills in &lt;code&gt;{shiny}&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ThinkR-open/golem&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{golem}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I also used GitHub to manage app enhancements and document workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the app boasts a sophisticated modeling component, estimating the demographic characteristics of populations within a given distance, or buffer, around the park or trail. We expect the update to roll out around Q2 2021.&lt;/p&gt;











&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-regional-parks-acs&#34; href=&#34;https://lizroten.com/media/albums/regional-parks-acs/percent_asian.PNG&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lizroten.com/media/albums/regional-parks-acs/percent_asian_hu91fa393d83e942f451387bae7d725cbb_564277_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;percent_asian.PNG&#34; width=&#34;309&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-regional-parks-acs&#34; href=&#34;https://lizroten.com/media/albums/regional-parks-acs/percent_hispanic.PNG&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lizroten.com/media/albums/regional-parks-acs/percent_hispanic_hu86c047115c69d4975b43b4dc31611b28_805849_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;percent_hispanic.PNG&#34; width=&#34;309&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Twin Cities Rent Trends</title>
      <link>https://lizroten.com/project/twin-cities-rent-trends/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lizroten.com/project/twin-cities-rent-trends/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Twin Cities Rent Trends&lt;/em&gt; is a dashboard for analyzing rental housing market trends in the seven-county Twin Cities region. Rent data can be difficult and costly to obtain, and different sources can yield significantly different values. This app allows users to compare each source and view the data at different geographic levels. Users can view rent trends, including absolute rent price, rents adjusted for inflation, and year-over-year percent change. Users can also visualize the relationship between rent and vacancy rates (not available for all data sources).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I built the app based on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ThinkR-open/golem&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{golem}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; framework, which builds the app repository as an R package. The result is a robust Shiny app, complete with testing and modular elements. The app integrates other package I&amp;rsquo;ve developed, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Metropolitan-Council/council.skeleton&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{council.skeleton}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Metropolitan-Council/councilR&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{councilR}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;screenshots&#34;&gt;Screenshots&lt;/h2&gt;











&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-twin-cities-rent-trends&#34; href=&#34;https://lizroten.com/media/albums/twin-cities-rent-trends/costar_vacancy.PNG&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lizroten.com/media/albums/twin-cities-rent-trends/costar_vacancy_huc792cfefd3b7fa975dbd88c4549745e2_401009_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;costar_vacancy.PNG&#34; width=&#34;255&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-twin-cities-rent-trends&#34; href=&#34;https://lizroten.com/media/albums/twin-cities-rent-trends/data_download.PNG&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lizroten.com/media/albums/twin-cities-rent-trends/data_download_hue2a3431dd02d014d62df9fd797e1e963_85462_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;data_download.PNG&#34; width=&#34;422&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-twin-cities-rent-trends&#34; href=&#34;https://lizroten.com/media/albums/twin-cities-rent-trends/home.PNG&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lizroten.com/media/albums/twin-cities-rent-trends/home_hu3ebdb204b5f4ede06cbf9f0321482f54_386558_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;home.PNG&#34; width=&#34;251&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-twin-cities-rent-trends&#34; href=&#34;https://lizroten.com/media/albums/twin-cities-rent-trends/zillow_neighborhood.PNG&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lizroten.com/media/albums/twin-cities-rent-trends/zillow_neighborhood_hue6f110d4aa210dd53bbcb02bd250c7a3_540348_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;zillow_neighborhood.PNG&#34; width=&#34;248&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID Traffic Trends</title>
      <link>https://lizroten.com/project/covid-traffic-trends/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lizroten.com/project/covid-traffic-trends/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In early 2020, the transportation and modeling team at the Metropolitan Council began using traffic data from the Minnesota Department of Transportation (MnDOT) to evaluate the impact of recent physical distancing efforts on regional and statewide travel. I developed an accompanying R Shiny app  with sections for visualizing the model results, downloading tabular data, and explaining the model. Individual items include an interactive plot showing the percent difference from expected traffic levels and an interactive map displaying the change in expected traffic at individual traffic sensors across the Twin Cities metro area and Rochester area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I built the app based on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ThinkR-open/golem&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{golem}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; framework, which builds the app repository as an R package. The result is a robust Shiny app, complete with testing and modularized elements. The app integrates other package I&amp;rsquo;ve developed, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Metropolitan-Council/council.skeleton&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{council.skeleton}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Metropolitan-Council/councilR&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{councilR}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The first iteration of the app was published within a week of starting on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;screenshots&#34;&gt;Screenshots&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plot shows the daily relative decrease in freeway travel over time across the Twin Cities metropolitan region after March 1. Points that fall below the zero-line represent decreases in travel relative to typical travel on that day of the year and day of the week. Typical travel is estimated using a statistical analysis of traffic volumes from 2018, 2019, and 2020 prior to March 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;This plot shows the daily relative decrease in freeway travel over time across the Twin Cities metropolitan region after March 1. Points that fall below the zero-line represent decreases in travel relative to typical travel on that day of the year and day of the week. Typical travel is estimated using a statistical analysis of traffic volumes from 2018, 2019, and 2020 prior to March 1.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/covid-traffic-trends/covid_plot_hua311f75e57885d62d4e1346a426da407_68151_48f3670c773a50f2fcaa1c1a6956b92a.webp 400w,
               /project/covid-traffic-trends/covid_plot_hua311f75e57885d62d4e1346a426da407_68151_db7c1f14a84eb7512d5467994114efde.webp 760w,
               /project/covid-traffic-trends/covid_plot_hua311f75e57885d62d4e1346a426da407_68151_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://lizroten.com/project/covid-traffic-trends/covid_plot_hua311f75e57885d62d4e1346a426da407_68151_48f3670c773a50f2fcaa1c1a6956b92a.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;331&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The map shows the decreases in travel at individual traffic monitoring sites across the Twin Cities Metropolitan area. Traffic monitoring is performed by the Minnesota Department of Transportation (MnDOT) using detectors built into the infrastructure of the roads. These detectors are usually used to estimate congestion along Metro area highways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The map shows the decreases in travel at individual traffic monitoring sites across the Twin Cities Metropolitan area. Traffic monitoring is performed by the Minnesota Department of Transportation (MnDOT) using detectors built into the infrastructure of the roads. These detectors are usually used to estimate congestion along Metro area highways.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/covid-traffic-trends/covid_map_hu2b0fc36fb71bcf5228532290bcbba5fb_924282_e82576251e68046ee475b05d052f4dfc.webp 400w,
               /project/covid-traffic-trends/covid_map_hu2b0fc36fb71bcf5228532290bcbba5fb_924282_5769de13bb30b786b82fff4deca0312b.webp 760w,
               /project/covid-traffic-trends/covid_map_hu2b0fc36fb71bcf5228532290bcbba5fb_924282_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://lizroten.com/project/covid-traffic-trends/covid_map_hu2b0fc36fb71bcf5228532290bcbba5fb_924282_e82576251e68046ee475b05d052f4dfc.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;444&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;relevent-links&#34;&gt;Relevent links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metrocouncil.org/Transportation/Planning-2/Transit-Plans,-Studies-Reports/Highways-Roads/COVID-19.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Official news release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://metrotransitmn.shinyapps.io/covid-traffic-trends/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Live app site (updated regularly)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Metropolitan-Council/loop-sensor-trends&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Como Regional Park Hex Grid StreetLight Analysis</title>
      <link>https://lizroten.com/project/como-hex-streetlight-parks/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lizroten.com/project/como-hex-streetlight-parks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To better understand activity within Como Regional Park and how that activity shifts with the seasons, I created a hexagon grid over the park and then used aggregated and anonymized location-based services data provided by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.streetlightdata.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;StreetLight Data&lt;/a&gt; to measure relative activity in each hexagon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project was my first endeavor with Tableau and was used as a pilot before we dedicated additional resources to using StreetLight Data for parks research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;details&#34;&gt;Details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;streetlight-data&#34;&gt;StreetLight Data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data in this data visualization comes from StreetLight, an independent data provider which cleans, processes and assimilates millions of spatial data points from a combination of mobile phone Location-Based Services (LBS) data and GPS data. The data is anonymized, aggregated, and accessed only through specific analyses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This viz draws on LBS data. Cell phone apps that use LBS collect the device&amp;rsquo;s location in space and time. StreetLight detects trips, a movement with clear start and stop locations. StreetLight uses trips to create the StreetLight Traffic Index, which is a normalized measure of the relative traffic, or activity, in an area. The data’s spatial precision is 65ft or better and StreetLight estimates a 23% penetration rate for the combined US and Canada adult population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;analysis&#34;&gt;Analysis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this viz, we made a hexagon grid over Como Regional Park. We then ran a StreetLight analysis to measure the relative traffic in each hexagon and repeated the analysis for Winter (November 2017 - February 2018), Summer (May 2018 - August 2018), and all 2018. StreetLight returns a Traffic Index value for each hexagon for every trip intersection type, day type, and day part configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;interactive-map&#34;&gt;Interactive Map&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Tableau viz, you can view the analysis results. Each hexagon on the map changes color according to its Traffic Index, or activity level. The darker the color, the higher the traffic. You can view the exact Traffic Index value of any hexagon by hovering over it. Use the map tools in the upper left corner to pan, zoom, and adjust the map view. We suggest you view this story in full screen for the best display.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
